this is the last main video in the
series where we'll talk about
representations of Le groups and Lee
algebras in this video we're going to
talk about the representation theory of
SL2 C which is the double cover of the
lorence
group in the last few videos we studied
representations of rotations in 3D space
the standard 3x3 rotation matrices that
rotate 3D vectors are the SO3 matrices
these can be generated by generator
matrices in the SO3 Lee algebra if we
exponentiate them multiplied by an angle
the SO3 generators follow these
commutation
relations an alternative way to do 3D
rotations is to write the XY Z
components as a 2X two po vector and
rotate them using a pair of S2
matrices an individual su2 Matrix will
rotate a two component object called a
po spinner and su2 Le group matrices
have their own 2x two generators in the
Lee algebra
su2 these generators are from the su2
Lee algebra and they obey the same
commutation relations as s
SO3 these sets of rotation matrices of
different sizes are called
representations of the Le group su2 and
their generators are representations of
the Le algebra
su2 in previous videos we found that
there was one representation of su2 per
Dimension n which can also be labeled by
the Spin number J which equals the
dimension minus1 /
2 now we want to move to space time
where Lorent Transformations keep the
SpaceTime metric
constant the standard 4x4 lorence
transformation matrices that transform
4D space time vectors form the lorence
group s so
+13 these involve three rotations one
for each spacal plane and three boosts
for changing inertial frames one for
each spatial
Direction these 4x4 Lorent
transformation matrices can be generated
using these six generators from the Lee
algebra s so
+13 the rotation generators are labeled
by J with two subscripts that indicate
the plane of rotation the Boost
generators are labeled by K with one
time subscript and one space subscript
indicating the Boost
Direction sometimes these generators are
all labeled by the same letter like M or
S since the subscripts make it clear
what they
generate it's also common to label
rotation generators with a single index
for the axis they rotate around and
label boost generators with a single
index for the direction they boost
in these generators from the lorence
algebra obey these commutation
relations one thing I was not very clear
about in previous videos is that boost
generators can have either a plus sign
or a minus sign in front of them both
versions satisfy the expected
commutation relations for the lorence
algebra we can move from one sign
convention to the other just by doing a
change of coordinates where we reverse
the signs of the XY Z coordinates this
is like reflecting the universe in a
kind of three-dimensional
mirror this change of coordinates leaves
rotations unchanged since reversing both
directions in a plane does not change
the direction of rotation but this will
reverse the direction of boosts this
applies for both the Boost generators in
the Lee algebra and the Boost matrices
in the Lee Group which will boost in
opposite
directions an alternative way to do
Lorent Transformations is to write the
time XY Z components as a 2X two vile
vector and transform them using a pair
of SL2 C
matrices these are the six Lorent
Transformations on 4D SpaceTime vectors
written as double-sided SL2 C
Transformations an individual SL2 C
Matrix will Lorent transform a vile
spinner and and here are the SL2 C
generators these sets of matrices are
representations of the Le group SL2 C
and their generators are representations
of the Lee algebra SL2
C now before with the matrices that
transformed vectors we saw that boost
generators could have either plus signs
or minus signs but we could swap between
them using a change of vector
coordinates so these are equivalent
Matrix representations of the lorence
algebra with the matrices that transform
Spinners the Boost generators can also
have either plus signs or minus signs in
front the commutation relations work in
both
cases however we cannot swap between the
two cases using a change of spinner
basis so the generators with negative
boosts and positive boosts are actually
from two different Matrix
representations of the lorence algebra
ra called the left chyal and right chyal
spin 1/ half
representations the rotations are the
same but the boosts are reversed this
applies to the Lee algebra as well as
the Lee
group the fact that these left and right
representations exist is related to the
fact that the irreducible
representations of SL2 C are labeled by
two spin
values so we we end up with a
two-dimensional table of irreducible
representations with all possible pairs
of spin
values one consequence of this is that
there are two types of spinners in
SpaceTime left chyro Spinners and right
chyro Spinners but there are many other
irreducible representations as well for
the rest of this video we're going to
explain how to get this table of SL2 C
representations and talk about how some
of the representation
relate to objects in physics like four
vectors the electromagnetic tensor and
the metric
tensor so in SL 2C we have six
generators three rotation generators
denoted by J's and three boost
generators denoted by K's here I'm using
the notation where the J index gives the
rotation axis and the K index gives the
Boost
Direction the commutate of two rotation
generators gives a rotation generator
the commutator of two boost generators
gives a rotation generator and the
commutator of a rotation and a boost
generator gives a boost generator all
other commutators not listed here go to
zero we can take these six basis
generators and change basis by defining
the A's which are a rotation generator
plus I times the corresponding boost
generator
ided
two we can Define the be's in the same
way but with the signs in front of the
Boost generators changed to be
negative note that since we're allowing
complex coefficients in these linear
combinations we've actually switched to
the complexified version of the SL2 C Le
algebra which is denoted with this
subscript
C in this new basis the A's follow these
commutation relations the B's follow
these commutation relations and the A's
and B's commute with each other so in
this basis the commutators split nicely
into two separate
families each of these two families is
equivalent to an su2 Lee algebra because
these are the same commutation relations
seen with
su2 as seen in video 18 whenever we have
an su2 Lee algebra we can change bases
to get a raising operator a lowering
operator and an igen value operator
according to these
definitions since these definitions
involve complex numbers these operators
belong to complexified su2 Lee
algebras this change of basis from the
J's and K's to the A's and B's means the
complexified SL2 C Le algebra is
equivalent to the direct sum of two
complexified su2 Le
algebras if we have a loren
transformation L from the group SL2 C we
can write the lorence transformation L
as an exponential of the generators in
the SL2 C Le algebra so we have a linear
combination containing the J rotation
generators multiplied by circular angles
and the K boost generators multiplied by
hyperbolic
angles we can also write this linear
combination using the notation where the
J and K generators only have one
index we can change this basis to the
A's and B's as I showed earlier where
each generator gets its own coefficient
beside it since this change of basis
involves complex coefficients we're now
in the complexified SL2 C
algebra we can now change basis once
again to the latter and igen value
operators and each of the these are a
complexified su2
algebra so here we can clearly see that
the complexified SL2 C algebra is
equivalent to the direct sum of a pair
of complexified su2
algebras this is made obvious when we do
this simple change of
basis now recall that if leag group
members X and Y commute then we can use
the property where the exponential of a
sum becomes the product of exponentials
so if we take the exponential of a
linear combination of our SL2 C
generators since the A and B generators
commute with each other we can rewrite
this as a product of two exponentials
one containing the a copies of su2
generators and the other containing the
B copies of su2
generators what this means is we can
always write a complexified SL2 C group
member L as the product of two Le group
elements UA and U which are each
generated from complexified
S2s because their generators commute the
A and B group members also commute with
each
other so if we have two Lorent matrices
L1 and L2 we can decompose each of them
into a product of uas and
U's if we compose the L's because the A
and B versions of the use commute with
each other we can swap these elements
and up with a product of uas times a
product of
U's so we can write a complexified
lorence group element as an ordered pair
of complexified su2 group elements and
when multiplying group elements together
the a elements and B elements just slide
past each other and multiply with
themselves because of this we say the
complexified lorence group can be
written as the direct product of
complexified su2 subgroup
groups this direct product symbol
indicates members from the two subgroups
are written as ordered pairs where the
left elements multiply with left
elements and right elements multiply
with right
elements incidentally this is exactly
the property that the tensor product
follows when we compose a pair of tensor
product elements
together so so far we've been discussing
the abstract properties of the lorence
group and lorence
algebra but now I'd like to talk about
their Matrix
representations a matrix representation
row of the complexified lorence group
will map every group element to an
invertible N byn
Matrix since the group elements can be
decomposed into a product we can also
decompose The Matrix representation into
a tensor product of a left
representation row L for the a elements
and a right representation row r for the
B
elements and remember to get the
generator of a tensor product of group
matrices we take the derivative using
product rule then set the parameter to
zero and we get this formula here with
the sum of two tensor products involving
generator
matrices so a Lee algebra representation
Pi will map complexified SL2 C
generators to n byn
matrices as we saw if we have a tensor
product representation we can take the
generators of the various algebra
elements and represent them using this
formula okay so I realize we've been
dealing with a lot of abstract math and
we'll get to examples soon but let's sum
up everything we've learned the
complexified Lorent algebra can be
broken up into the direct sum of a pair
of complexified su2 algebras that
commute with each other as a result the
complexified Lorent group elements can
be written as the product of a pair of
complexified su2 group
elements as a result Matrix
representations of the lorence group can
be written as the tensor product of two
complexified su2 group
representations called the left and
right
representations and Lorent algebra
representations are given by this
formula so in order to get an
irreducible representation of the
lorence algebra we need to pick two
irreducible su2
representations one for the left term
and one for the right
term we already know there is exactly
one irreducible su2 representation per
Dimension so we can label the lorence
algebra representations by two integers
M and N which are the dimensions of the
left and right representations
respectively we can also also label
these by the Spin numbers JL and Jr
which are equal to the dimensions -1 /
2 I also want to clarify the difference
between the dimension of a Lee algebra
and the dimension of a Lee algebra
representation the dimension of a Lee
algebra is just the number of
independent generators in the
algebra so SL2 C is a six-dimensional
algebra because it has six generators
which act as the six basis vectors for
the vector
space similarly su2 is a
three-dimensional Lee algebra because it
has three
generators the dimension of a
representation however is the size of
the matrices used in a matrix
representation so while the SL2 C Le
algebra is always a six-dimensional
algebra its Matrix representations can
have different dimensions like 1 2 3 and
so
on so this direct sum here indicates we
are combining two sets of
three-dimensional Lee algebra generators
into a space with six
generators whereas this tensor product
indicates we are taking the tensor
product of representation matrices thus
multiplying the dimensions of the
representation
spaces Okay so let's start looking for
Matrix representations of the J rotation
and K boost
generators we know the formulas for the
A's and B's and we can reverse these
formulas to solve for J and
K if we have a matrix representation row
of a rotation Matrix generated by J we
can rewrite J in terms of A and B since
A and B commute we can split this into a
product of
exponentials as we explained previously
we can write these commuting group
members as an ordered pair and the
Matrix representation can be written as
a tensor product of a left
representation row L for the left group
member and a right representation row R
for the right group
member to get the generator
representation matrices we take the
derivative and set the parameter to zero
the derivative gives product rule over
the tensor product and after we set the
parameter to zero these terms become
generators in The Matrix representations
denoted by pi and these terms become
identity
matrices we can get a similar formula
for boosts except the formula has a
minus sign in the middle and is
multiplied by an overall factor of
netive
I it's worth noting that while the A's
and B's live in the complexified SL2 C
Le algebra because of the complex
coefficients the J's and K's live in the
real version of SL2 C and coefficients
are assumed to be
real so we have these formulas for the J
and K generator Matrix
representations we just need to pick su2
EPS for pi L and pi r we can say the
left representation will have Dimension
M with spin JL and the right
representation will have Dimension n
with spin
Jr so now the matrices on the left side
of the tensor products have size M and
the matrices on the right side of the
tensor products have size n and the
Matrix representations of the J's and Ks
are denoted by two integers M and N
alternatively we can denote it by two
spin values JL and
Jr now we can start exploring this table
of eps by choosing different
combinations of Dimensions M and N or
spin values JL and
Jr the scalar representation is where
the dimensions M and N are both equal to
one in terms of the spins both the left
and right spin values are zero the 1 by
one or spin zero representation of any
su2 Matrix is the 1ex one Matrix
containing a zero so for the m = 1 Nal 1
representation of a rotation generator J
when we subin our representation
matrices these zero matrices make both
terms in the sum go to zero so we end up
with just a zero
Matrix the same is true for the
representations of the Boost
matrices so for the m equals 1 Nal 1
representation of SL2 C all the
generator matrices are zero
when we exponentiate these generator
matrices to get matrices in the Le group
SL2 C we just get one by one identity
matrices what this means is that
particles which transform under this
representation are completely unchanged
by rotations and boosts these
Transformations are equivalent to just
multiplying by one for this reason
objects that transform under this
representation are called scalers they
look the same in all reference
frames now let's look at the spin 1/2
representations for su2 the spin 1/2 EP
also called the 2x2 EP matrices are
given by neg a half * pairs of poi
matrices let's look at the m = 2 N = 1
in terms of spins this is the 1 12 comma
EP for rotation matrices since the
second term in the sum is the 1 by one
EP it goes to zero and can be ignored
for the first term we have our 2x two EP
tensored with the 1x1 identity Matrix
this tensor operation leaves the 2x2
matrix unchanged so we're just left with
our standard 2x two
ER for boosts we get something similar
except there's a factor of negative I in
front of The Matrix
so in this EP rotation generators are
given by su2 and boost generators are
given by negative I *
su2 we know su2 generators are just -
one2 time pairs of Sigma
matrices for boosts we multiply by NE I
but there's a property for the sigma
matrices where if we multiply a pair of
sigmas * I we just get the third Sigma
so the Boost matrices are just - one2
times an individual Sigma corresponding
to the Boost
Direction so these are the generators
for the m = 2 Nal
1 and when we exponentiate them we get
these rotation and boost
matrices particles that transform under
this representation are called vial
Spinners specifically left chyro vial
Spinners now this is not the only spin
1/2
representation we can also look at the m
= 1 n = 2 EP in terms of spins this is
the 0 comma 1 12
EP if we look at the formula for the
rotation generators this time the first
term in the sum goes to zero once again
we're left with an su2
representation this time we're
representing the B generators instead of
the a generators but since the A's and
B's both denote su2 generators this is
still the 2x2 su2
representation however with the Boost
formula the first term goes to zero and
the second term contains a minus sign
this cancels with the minus sign out in
front and we get multiplication by plus
I this has the opposite sign compared to
what we saw for boosts in the left chyal
representation so in this EP rotation
generators are given by su2 and boost
generators are given by plus I *
su2 the generators and their lorence
Transformations look like this these
transform right chyro vial
Spinners so we have two different
spinner representations of the lorence
group the rotation generators are the
same in both cases but the Boost
generators have opposite signs we call
these the left chyal and right chyal
spinner
representations now it's important to
note that we cannot swap between the
left and right chyal representations
using a change of spinner basis I proved
this in video 9 so these two
representations are not equivalent
representations the left and right chyal
particles they transform are indeed
different however we can swap between
these two representations by changing
the signs of all the sigmas the rotation
generators are unchanged since the two
negative signs cancel but the Boost
generators do change sign so we can
think of the left and right chyro
representations as being related to each
other by reflecting the universe in a
three-dimensional mirror where the XY Z
coordinates are all sent to their
negative
versions the same rule applies to the s
l2c Le group matrices that we get by
exponentiating the
generators the rotations are the same
but the boosts have their signs
reversed if we take the direct sum of
the left and right spinner
representations the left and right chyro
vial Spinners stack on top of each other
and give us a dra spinner dra Spinners
transform with 4x4 block diagonal
matrices consisting of a left Kyro SL2 C
block and a right chyro SL2 C
block also if we take the four gamma
matrices written in the vile or chyal
basis and multiply them all together
along with the complex I we get a new
Matrix which is normally called gamma
5 if we multiply gamma 5 by a direct
spinner with only the left components
non zero we get that same direct spinner
* -1 and if we multiply gamma 5 by a
direct spinner with only the right
components non zero we get that same
direct spinner time +
one so left and right vile Spinners are
the minus1 and + one igen spaces of the
gamma 5
operator we can also use gamma 5 to
define the left and right projectors PL
and PR these projectors Square to
themselves and add to
one they can project out the left and
right components of a direct spinner
which can then be added together again
to give the original direct
spinner now let's look at the m = 2 n =
representation in terms of spins this is
the 1 12 comma 1/2
representation this is the
representation that transforms 4D
SpaceTime
vectors when looking at the formulas for
rotation generators both the SU two
generators and the identity matrices are
2x two and so their tensor products
result in 4x4
matrices the same is true for Boost
generators now to get the actual group
representation matrices that do Lorent
Transformations we need to exponentiate
these generator
matrices before I do that I want to go
over a few
properties if we have a formula of the
form a Tor identity applied to Identity
tensor B then by tensor product rules we
can apply first to first and second to
second to get a tensor B this also
equals identity tensor B applied to a
tensor identity so the two terms commute
with each
other next if we exponentiate a tensor
identity we get an infinite Series in
powers of a tensor identity if we look
at the squared term and do the
application
we end up with a squared tensor
identity so really the nth power of this
expression is just a to the N tensor
identity this means that in our
exponential series we can move the
exponent to the a then use the tensor
product rules to apply the scalers to
the A and also factor out the identity
from the right in all terms in the sum
so we end up with an exponential series
tensored with the identity which means
the whole thing is equal to e to the a
tensor
identity we get a similar expression for
the exponential of identity tensor
B using these properties we can now take
the rotation generator representation
formula and exponentiate it we know
these two terms in the sum commute so we
can rewrite it as a product of
exponentials note that the tensor
product rules require that we pass the
scalar Theta to only one term in the
tensor
product now we can apply the
exponentials to the A and B
representations then apply first to
first and second to Second and we get
this tensor product as the final
result we get a similar formula for
boosts except the signs and the
exponentials are
reversed so given these SL2 C algebra IR
formulas we get these SL2 C group gr
formulas this shows the SL2 C group ER
matrices can be factored into a tensor
product of complexified su2
matrices so for our m = 2 Nal 2 EP of
the SL2 C group we get a tensor product
of left and right 2x two complexified
S2s now since complexifying the argument
of an su2 rotation Matrix gives a boost
these two matrices are equivalent to to
left and right 2x two SL2 C
matrices so this tensor product property
is a bit abstract so let's look at how
this works out with actual Matrix
components we know the left spinner
Lorent algebra representation has these
six matrices the anti- Herm Mission
rotation generators give unitary
rotation matrices and the Herm Mission
boost generators give Herm Mission boost
matrices
the right spinner representation
matrices are the same but the boosts go
in the opposite
direction in other words these are the
inverses of the left boost
matrices now if we take an S2 C Matrix L
and take its Herm Mission conjugate then
take its inverse for the unitary
rotation matrices since the inverse is
the hermiss conjugate the combination of
hermiss conjugate and inverse operations
cancel out and the Matrix is unchanged
but for Boost matrices which are Herm
Mission the Herm Mission conjugate does
nothing so we're left with just the
inverse which reverses the Boost
Direction so if a matrix L belongs to
the left spinner representation of SL2 C
then the Herm Mission conjugate inverse
of L belongs to the right spinner
representation of SL2 C again this
operation leaves rotations the same but
reverses the
boosts now in video 9 I also introduced
a kind of scalar product for vial
Spinners which uses this Epsilon
Matrix this product is left unchanged by
Lorent
Transformations which leads to the
property that L transpose Epsilon L
equals Epsilon this can be Rewritten in
a number of ways
if we look at this scaler product we can
identify this sigh as a left vial
spinner and identify s transpose Epsilon
as a left Dual vial spinner if we
complex conjugate this entire formula we
can identify s transpose conjugate
Epsilon as a right vial spinner and
identify s conjugate as a right dual
vial
spinner so we previously talked about
the left and right spinner
representations so where do these dual
left and dual right Spinners come from
it turns out these are not from new
representations we can flip between the
left and left Dual Spinners by invoking
the transpose and using Epsilon as a
change of spinner coordinates
Matrix the same is true for changing
between the right and right dual
Spinners so the Dual spinner
representations are are not new they're
ultimately just a change of coordinates
from the spinner representations we
already
know for matrices the change of
coordinates is done by using
multiplication by Epsilon and Epsilon
inverse on either side so the left and
left Dual representations are equivalent
and the right and right dual
representations are
equivalent using the algebraic
properties we've learned so far we can
deduce that taking a left chyu SL2 C
Matrix L and complex conjugating it
gives the corresponding right chyal dual
SL2 C
Matrix this is a fact we'll keep in mind
for
later remember we can rewrite A
four-dimensional Spacetime Vector as a
vial Vector which is lorence transformed
using an SL2 C Matrix L on one side and
El dger on the other side if we take
this double-sided Loren transformation
formula and turn through the Matrix
multiplications to get four equations we
can summarize all the coefficients using
this 4x4
Matrix this 4x4 Matrix is really just
the tensor product of a left SL2 C
Matrix L and its complex conjugate which
remember is the corresponding SL2 C
Matrix from the Dual right
representation which is equivalent to
the right representation under a change
of
coordinates now this 4D SpaceTime Vector
has all the components mixed together
but we can separate them using this
change of coordinates Matrix C we can
then take our 4x4 Matrix and change
coordinates using C and C inverse on
either side to get a lorence matrix
which transforms familiar 4D SpaceTime
vectors so when we tensor the left
spinner and right spinner
representations of SL2 C together we
really do get a 4x4 lorence group
representation which transforms 4D
SpaceTime
vectors so the tensor product of the
left spinner representation and the
right spinner representation really does
give us the vector
representation now let's look at the m =
3 n = 1
representation in terms of spins this is
the one comma 0 representation
the 3D representation of su2 matrices is
the same as the case of the generators
for standard 3 by3 rotation
matrices as we saw before when one of
the representations is 1 by one its term
in the sum goes to zero and the tensor
product with the 1ex one identity
doesn't change the result so we end up
with the standard 3x3 rotation
generators and for boosts we just
multiply them by
I now for the m = 1 n = 3
representation in terms of spins this is
the 0 comma 1
representation we get the exact same
thing as before except now it's the
first term in the sum that goes to zero
and as a result for the boosts we get
multiplication by plus I
instead so once again we've ended up
with left and right representations
where the rotations are the same but the
boosts are reversed with opposite signs
these are the left spin one
representation and the right spin one
representation the six Lee algebra
generators are 3x3 matrices and they can
be exponentiated into these 3x3 Le group
matrices but what do these correspond to
physically well if we combine the two
representations together using the
direct sum we get a six-dimensional
representation which transforms the six
components of the electromagnetic field
also called the Faraday
tensor vectors in 4D SpaceTime have four
components but the electromagnetic field
has six
components this is because the
electromagnetic field is not a vector
it's a bi Vector in 4D space time there
are six different ways we can group
pairs of basis vectors together into B
VOR
vectors I'm going to use the Clifford
algebra notation from videos 11 and 12
and denote basis vectors using the gamas
and basis bi vectors using pairs of
gamas the bi vectors that include one
time Direction and one space Direction
correspond to the electric field e since
the electric field can linearly
accelerate charged particles thereby
giving it more energy and more
momentum the B vectors made of two space
directions correspond to the magnetic
field B since they can cause a Charged
particle to circle using centripetal
acceleration which exchanges two of the
momentum directions but doesn't change
the
energy but how does this fit in with the
1 comma 0 some 0 comma 1 lorence
representation if you recall we
previously used gamma 5 to separate a
dra spinner into left and right
halves the left half had an igen value
of minus1 and the right half had an IG
value of + one under gamma
5 we can do something similar by
applying gamma 5 to the electromagnetic
field remember squaring the gamas gives
either + one or minus one and swapping
the order of two different gamas gives
us a minus sign in
front if we apply gamma 5 to the gamma T
gamma Zed by vector after swapping and
Computing the squares we get I gamma X
gamma Y which is another B
Vector so gamma 5 has the effect of
turning bi vectors into other bi vectors
here's the action of gamma 5 on all the
B
vectors using these rules we can build
these three linear combinations of basis
by vectors when gamma 5 acts on these it
Returns the Same by vectors but with a
negative - one in front
in other words these are igen B vectors
of gamma 5 with igen values of
-1 now if we take these three B vectors
and reflect the spatial directions so
that gamma's x y and Zed become negative
we get another set of three B
vectors when we act on these B vectors
with gamma 5 we get ion values of + one
instead sometimes you'll see these B
vectors mul multiplied by an overall
factor of -1 but this doesn't change
their igen values they still span the
same + one igen
space so we've divided the
six-dimensional space of SpaceTime by
vectors into a pair of threedimensional
subspaces the minus one and + one igen
spaces under gamma 5 and we get from one
Subspace to the other by mirroring the
spatial Dimensions XY Z
we can also use the left and right
projectors we defined previously to
split the electromagnetic field tensor
into left and right
halves it turns out that these minus1
and + one igen spaces transform
independently under Lorent
transformations to prove this we just
need to show that the plus one and
minus1 igen values are unchanged when we
do a loren
transformation let's take a by Vector
Alpha with igen value + one from video
12 on spin groups we know that we can
lorence transform this by Vector using a
double-sided
exponential note that because we're in
space time the left exponential has a
plus sign and the right exponential has
a minus sign recall that we can expand
this exponential using Oilers formula to
give a scalar cosine term and a bi
Vector sign term and we use hyperbolic
trig functions if we're doing a
boost now we want to apply gamma 5 to
this Lorent transformed version of Alpha
and show that the igen value has not
changed this is easy to do because gamma
5 commutes with all B vectors in space
time so we can slide gamma 5 past the
exponential have it act on Alpha to give
+ one then bring the plus one back out
in front so the Lorent transformed
version of alpha retains the same igen
value of +
one a similar proof can be shown for a
by Vector beta that has an igen value of
minus1 so the + one and minus1 IG spaces
are indeed invariant under lorence
Transformations the B vectors with I
value minus one are called anti-self
dual by vectors these transform with the
1 comma 0 lorence representation and
correspond to left circularly polarized
electromagnetic waves the bi vectors
with igen value + one are called
self-dual by vectors these transform
with the 0 comma 1 Lorent representation
and they correspond to right circularly
polarized electromagnetic
waves so we can take our electromagnetic
Faraday tensor and perform this change
of basis to the igen by Vector
basis the components of f in the new bi
Vector basis become complex linear
combinations of the E and B
fields as we showed each of these two
igen spaces transforms independently
under Lorent
Transformations so we can transform this
six component column using a 6x6 Matrix
which is broken into 3x3 block diagonal
sections these 3x3 blocks are the 1
comma 0 and 0 comma 1 Lorent
representation
as an aside this form of the
electromagnetic field is called the
remon Silverstein
Vector we can identify these two igen
spaces with left and right circularly
polarized electromagnetic
waves the cross product of the E and B
fields will always give the direction of
electromagnetic wave
propagation so we can Define left
circular waves as having the B field leg
behind the E field by a quarter phase
with negative I and right circular waves
will have the B field lead the E field
by a quarter phase with plus
I looking back at our six component
column in the left circular case only
the top half is nonzero and for the
right circular case only the bottom half
is non
zero so these really do represent the
left and right circular polarizations of
the electromagnetic
field you can pause if you want to look
at the details but this is how the anti-
selfdual B vectors
rotate this is how they
boost and here's how the formulas line
up with the representation
matrices it's also worth noting that the
way we mixed the E and B fields to get a
nice splitting into two parts is exactly
the same mixing of the rotation and
boost generators in the lorence algebra
that we did to split the lorence algebra
into two pieces and the selfdual and
anti-self-dual basis vectors we defined
are algebraically equivalent to the A's
and
B's and as another aside the concept of
self-dual and anti-self-dual by vectors
is usually defined using the Hodge star
operator in differential
geometry however in SpaceTime the hodg
star gives imaginary igen values whereas
gamma 5 gives real igen values so I used
gamma 5 in this video to get real igen
values finally we'll look at the m = 3
Nal 3 representation in terms of spins
this is the 1 comma 1
representation getting the generators
involves the tensor product of a pair of
3x3 matrices so we'll end up with 9 by9
matrices this is related to transforming
rank two tensors in space
time we're going to focus on covariant
rank two SpaceTime tensors which have
two lower
indices these take two vectors as input
and produce a scalar in Array notation
the rank two tensor m is a 4x4
Matrix and the input vectors V transpose
and W are sandwiched on either
side now if we Loren transform the
vectors with a lorence matrix Lambda
inverse
then to ensure we get the same scalar
result in the new reference frame M must
transform with Lambda transpose and
Lambda on either
side M has 16 components so it
transforms under a 16 dimensional
representation of the lorence group this
means we could choose to write M as a 16
component column and write the tensor
product of lambdas as a 16x16
transformation matrix
now we can Define the symmetric part of
M as a Matrix S which equals m + m
transpose ID 2 and we can Define the
anti- symmetric part of M as M minus M
transpose /
2 s is symmetric so s transpose equals s
and a is anti-symmetric so a transpose
equals
a and if we add s and a back together we
get M
back if we lorence transform the
symmetric part s the result is also
symmetric and if we Loren transform the
anti-symmetric part A the result is also
anti-symmetric so when we have a
covariant Rank 2 tensor in SpaceTime the
10 symmetric components and the six
anti- symmetric components transform
independently from each other so the 16
dimensional repr representation
decomposes into the direct sum of 10 and
six dimensional
representations now the 10-dimensional
symmetric representation can be
decomposed further because the trace of
a rank two tensor is invariant in all
coordinate
systems now we have to be careful here
if we take the Matrix for our rank two
covariant tensor M the sum of the
diagonal elements is not invariant under
a
transformation instead we need to raise
an index using the inverse metric tensor
G we're taking the metric G to be a
covariant rank two tensor so it lorence
transforms like this we're also assuming
it's invariant under Loren
Transformations so g equals the Loren
transformed version of G and that leads
to this
property after we apply G inverse to M
this raises an index and we get a one
contravariant one covariant version of
M now when we sum the diagonal elements
we get the invariant trace of M this
version of M transforms with Lambda
inverse on the left instead of Lambda
transpose and this is what makes the
trace invariant under Loren
Transformations I'm going to define the
Matrix T to be the identity Matrix times
the trace of M over four basically the
four diagonal elements each hold a
quarter of the trace of M and so they
sum gives the trace of M so the trace of
T equals the trace of
M since both the trace and the identity
Matrix are unchanged by Loren
Transformations this T Matrix is also
unchanged by Loren
Transformations and so T acts like a
scaler we can get the CO variant version
of T by applying the metric G to it to
lower one of its
indices using the properties of the
metric we now see this new GT Matrix is
invariant under Lorent Transformations
for covariant Rank 2
matrixes so this GT Matrix behaves like
a
scaler so the 10-dimensional symmetric
representation s further breaks down
into a one-dimensional trace part given
by GT
and a nine-dimensional symmetric
traceless part given by S minus
GT the nine-dimensional part is the EP
transformed by the 1 comma 1 irreducible
Lorent
representation so to sum up a Rank 2
covariant tensor M has 16
components this breaks up into the
direct sum of several sub
representations the nine component
symmetric traceless part the six
component and anti symmetric part and
the one component Trace
part rank two tensors can be thought of
as tensor products of pairs of rank one
vectors so in SpaceTime M lives in the
representation space of the tensor
product of two 1 12 comma 1/2 EPS which
are the vector
EPS this decomposes into the direct sum
of several ARS the one component Trace
part is the 0 comma 0 scalar
ER the nine component traceless
symmetric part is the 1 comma 1 a and
the six component anti-symmetric part is
given by the 1 comma 0 su0 comma 1
representation which is exactly what we
saw for the electromagnetic tensor which
is also an anti-symmetric rank two
tensor in
SpaceTime so to sum up this video we
learned that if we took the six
generators of the SL2 C Le algebra and
changed basis to the A's and B's using
complex coefficients we could decompose
the complexified SL2 C Le algebra into
two copies of the complexified su2
algebras and this means elements of the
SL2 C Le group can be decomposed into
pairs of elements from the complexified
su2 Le
groups so to understand and the
irreducible representations of the SL2 C
Le group and Lee algebra we just need to
pick two irreducible representations of
the su2 Le group and Lee algebra and
take their tensor
product the two irreducible su2
representations can either be identified
by their Dimensions M and N or their
spin values J left and J
right by picking different values for
the spin number numbers we can write out
all the irreducible representations of
SL2 C using a two-dimensional
table EPS in the First Column are called
Left
representations and EPS in the first row
are called right
representations we can flip back and
forth between left and right
representations just by reversing the
spatial XY Z directions using minus
signs we can also identify left and
right representations using the igen
values of the gamma 5 operator and
project out left and right sub
representations using the left and right
projectors